Mort Weisinger Papers
Mort Weisinger Papers
1932-1965
Weisinger, Mort, 1915-
1.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American Jewish author, editor of DC Comics' Superman and contributing editor for This Week Magazine. Collection includes correspondence (1941-1965), mostly from magazine editors; and writings (1932-1957), including typescript draft and manuscript articles, most of which appeared in Coronet and This Week Magazine.
148741
Biographical History
Mort Weisinger (1915-1978) was an American Jewish author, editor of DC Comics' Superman and contributing editor for This Week Magazine.
Born in New York and raised in the Bronx, Weisinger was active in early science fiction fan clubs and fanzines; while still in high school he and several friends, including science fiction guru Forrest Ackerman, co-founded The Time Traveler, the first 'zine to focus entirely on science fiction. Weisinger attended, but did not graduate from, New York University, leaving in 1934 to start Solar Sales Service, an agency for science fiction writers and artists.
In March 1941 Weisinger took a job with National Periodicals which later became DC Comics. Apart from a brief absence to serve in the Special Services during World War II, Weisinger remained at DC for more than thirty years. Among his achievements with DC were the creation of Aquaman, Green Arrow and Johnny Quick, and of the Lois Lane and Jimmy Olsen spin-off series. He served as editor for Superman (creating such key elements as the effect of the yellow sun on Kryptonians and the Phantom Zone), Batman, and other important comics, and as editor for the Superman television series starring George Reeves. Near the end of his tenure he was named vice president of public relations for the company.
Weisinger also wrote on a wide range of topics, from beauty pageants to the Comics Code to a best-selling novel entitled The Contest (1970) and a book on Atomic Survival (1951). His articles appeared in The Saturday Evening Post, Reader's Digest and other national publications.
"It may seem corny to you, but one of the ways I was able to plot Superman was to pretend that I was Superman. What would my problems be, and how would I react if I were this magnificent character? It was like a schizoid personality. Instead of counting sheep when I had insomnia, I often fantasized what I would do as the Man of Steel."
[interview with Weisinger by Guy Lillian, July 1975]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Mort Weisinger Papers consist of correspondence and writings.
Correspondence consists of incoming letters from magazine editors and relate to the publication of Weisinger's work. Letters relating to particular articles in the Writings group of this collection are filed with the appropriate article, and the folders are labeled accordingly. Notable correspondents include Erle Stanley Gardner (1957) and Senator Margaret Chase Smith (1957); both are filed with the article "The day I cried."
Writings include manuscript and published copies of articles, a printed copy of one short story, and a printed copy of one comic book story. Topics covered in the articles run the gamut, from diet tips and traffic tickets to Superman and television quiz shows. Following the articles are copies of the magazines The Beam, The Beaver, and Time Traveler; Weisinger has several articles in each of these magazines, having served on the staff of The Beam and as associate editor of the others.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Writings are arranged alphabetically by type and within that by title.
Related Material
has more than one hundred collections relating to comic books, comic strips, and cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Journalism; Popular culture; Weisinger, Mort, 1915- -- Archives.; Authors, American.; Comic books, strips, etc.; Jews, American.; Periodical editors.; Science fiction, American.; Superman (Fictitious character); Articles.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.; Editors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mort Weisinger, 1968.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 1941-1965 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Accidentally ours, printed material Coronet (Box 1)
    - America's noisiest man, 1943-1944; correspondence, printed material Liberty, Reader's Digest (Box 1)
    - An animal's best friend, 1949-1950; correspondence, typescripts, typescript carbon, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 1)
    - An industry of charms, 1955-1956; correspondence, typescript carbon revised, printed material Coronet (Box 1)
    - The baby boom, 1954; correspondence, typescript, typescript carbon revised, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 1)
    - Baby buggies are big business, 1949-1950; correspondence, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 1)
    - Claws of the focus cats, Jun 1944; printed material Skyways (Box 1)
    - The day I cried, Feb 1958; correspondence, printed material Family Circle (Box 1)
    - Dr. Hollywood, 1955; typescript, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 1)
    - Don't panic over polio, 1952; correspondence, typescript carbon (Box 1)
    - Êles andam atrás do sey dinheiro!, 1957; printed material Reader's Digest (Box 1)
    - The fabulous house of Squibb, 1954; correspondence, typescript revised, printed material Coronet (Box 1)
    - Good times square, Oct 1944; printed material This Week Magazine (Box 1)
    - He fights firebugs, Jul 1949; printed material This Week Magazine (Box 1)
    - He finds jobs for ex-convicts, 1956; correspondence, typescripts, printed material Reader's Digest (Box 1)
    - Here comes Superman, 1946; correspondence, printed material Coronet (Box 1)
    - Home town news, Apr 1944; printed material This Week Magazine (Box 1)
    - How Ralph Edwards fools 'em, 1955; correspondence, printed material Family Circle (Box 1)
    - How they're cleaning up the comics, 1955; correspondence, typescript, printed material Better Homes and Gardens (Box 1)
    - How to fool the experts, Oct 1952; printed material This Week Magazine (Box 1)
    - How to look your picture best, 1958; correspondence, typescript revised, printed material Family Circle (Box 1)
    - I write from 0800 to 1800, Apr 1943; printed material Writer's Digest (Box 1)
    - If the tax man calls you in, 1953; correspondence, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 1)
    - I'm sick of waiters, 1954; correspondence, typescript carbons, printed material Coronet (Box 1)
    - I've got the most mysterious disease, 1954; correspondence, typescript revised, typescript carbon, printed material Saturday Evening Post (Box 1)
    - Kodak: Eyes of the world, 1954; correspondence, typescript carbon, printed material Coronet (Box 1)
    - Listen! Mark Twain speaking, Jul 1948; printed material Saturday Evening Post (Box 1)
    - Making good by mail, 1947; correspondence, typescript revised, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 1)
    - The man who takes wooden nickels, 1947; correspondence, typescript carbon, printed material Saturday Evening Post (Box 1)
    - Mr. Cheesebrough's wonder jelly, 1953; correspondence, typescript revised, printed material Coronet (Box 1)
    - Mister Gimmick, Nov 1947; printed material Collier's (Box 1)
    - Mr. Morse started something, 1953; correspondence, typescript carbon, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 2)
    - Moderne Bank auf Kundenfang, Jul 1953; printed material Das beste aus Reader's Digest (Box 2)
    - A new way to diet, 1953; correspondence, typescript carbon, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 2)
    - Romance of the cash register, 1954; correspondence, typescript carbon, printed material Coronet (Box 2)
    - Should you fight a traffic ticket?, 1953; correspondence, typescript, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 2)
    - Sleeping pills are worse than dope, 1955; correspondence, printed material Coronet (Box 2)
    - Snapshots on a shoestring, Oct 1943; printed material Coronet (Box 2)
    - Speaking of pictures, 1943; printed material Life (Box 2)
    - Star spangled business, 1947; correspondence, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 2)
    - Street corner king, Jul 1952; printed material This Week Magazine (Box 2)
    - Super-store for Jersey shoppers, 1952; correspondence, outline, original typescript, printed material Coronet (Box 2)
    - Swooning in the gloom, 1948; correspondence, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 2)
    - Tax chiselers beware, 1954; correspondence, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 2)
    - 10 diet tricks to make you lose weight, 1957; typescript carbon, printed material Family Circle (Box 2)
    - They're out to get your money, 1957; correspondence, typescripts carbons revised, printed material Banking, Reader's Digest (Box 2)
    - We’re living on tokens, 1955; correspondence, typescript carbon, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 2)
    - What you don't know about TV quiz shows, 1957; correspondence, typescript carbon, printed material Family Circle (Box 2)
    - Who gets drafted and when, Oct 1965; printed material This Week Magazine (Box 2)
    - Will your son be a chip off the old block, 1956; correspondence, typescript carbon, printed material This Week Magazine (Box 2)
    - A Yank at Yale, Sep 1944; printed material (incomplete), printed material Writer's Digest (Box 2)
    - Your car may be next, Feb 1949; printed material This Week Magazine (Box 2)
    - Your fabulous frankfurter, 1953; correspondence, typescript carbon, printed material Coronet (Box 2)
    - The Beam, 1952 (Box 2)
    - The Beaver, 1943-1944 (Box 2)
    - The Time Traveler, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Comic book stories
    - "Superman," Superman Comics, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Short stories
    - Ask me no questions, in This Week Magazine, Jun 1944 (Box 2)